Breaking maths news. A millennium
problem has been solved by AI. And yes,
it's covered in drama. But the point is, we
now have a millennium mass problem solution.
And normally when these things are announced
and I have to respond quickly, I'm on vacation
at the beach. But this time, do not worry. I
am not on vacation. At least not at the beach.
[music]
Yes, I am actually here at Disney World on
vacation. Or am I? Wait for the end of the
video. But the point is I'm hanging out with
my mates, but I thought I'd take some time off
to talk about this because it is a big deal.
The Millennium Prize problems were set up in
2000 as like the seven biggest most important
for some definition of that problems we have
to try and solve. And so far only one of them
have been solved and now suddenly one maybe
two that'll be a different video. But the point
is OpenAI have declared they have a solution to
the Navier Stokes equations. And whenever you
see the reporting on this that's been happening
this week people go oh Navier Stokes something
to do with like you know fluids moving around.
But not here. This is standup maths. We want to
know what those equations actually are and what
are the variables. Fluid movement is complicated.
There's a lot going on and the velocity a fluid is
moving at can change based on where it is in the
fluid. It's ridiculous. We're going to need some
complicated equations for this. It's not like it's
just one particle bumping off another one. Then
we can use force equals mass time acceleration.
Ah oh. F= ma. Forget that equation. We need the
Navier Stokes equations. Now you can formulate
them different ways. I'm going to use the way
the Clay Mathematics Institute writes them down
on their Navia Stokes equation page here. If
you scroll down when they actually officially
describe the problem, thanks Charles. Uh you
can see right there at the top the Navia Stokes
equations specifically three of them and we can
have a closer look at these. Here they are as
written or bear in mind technically within these
ranges. So x actually represents that is like all
three coordinates which are each a real value and
that's true for all of these. And then uh t starts
at zero and gets bigger. Pretty straightforward.
Oh and that end there should be three. That's the
number of dimensions we're working on um in this
case. Now, of the three, the last two are pretty
boring. We'll deal with them first. This one
here just says at the beginning, the fluid is, you
know, doing something something nice because u the
velocity is a function of x. That's the position
in in 3D coordinates. And at time, time zero,
that's just some, you know, u u prime starting
conditions. So, we don't have to worry about
that too much. This just means the fluid cannot be
compressed. It's an incompressible fluid. You try
and you try and squash it down. Nah, not going to
happen. So, those two are just setting the scene.
Here's the real thing. This is the equation we
worry about. This is telling us how the fluid
as a whole. All the particles together are moving
around. We'll look at the left hand side first.
And so, you've still got U there. All the U's
are the velocity of one particular bit of fluid,
which is what the I is specifying. And this is its
derivative with respect to time. You're thinking,
well, hang on, Matt. That can't all be the
derivative. Surely this there's your derivative of
velocity with respect to time. Well, I don't know
what this whole thing over here is doing. Well,
the reason we need this is because it's not just
like we're tracking one particle and its change of
its velocity, which is changing over time. The
speed of a packet of fluid can change based on
where it moves. It might move somewhere where the
velocity of that location is different. We need
all of this because the velocity u is a function
of the location in 3D space as well as being a
function of time. And actually the location in 3D
space. I've put this extra function of t in there.
You don't often see it um drawn this way. I want
to emphasize the velocity is a function of both
time and its position in 3D space which itself is
a function of time. It gets complicated. is if you
want to take the derivative of all of this with
respect to time, it's chain rule time. There it
is. So that's why at the front here, we've got
the partial derivative with respect to t. And
then we got to add in all the other ones. In fact,
there's just one for each of the three different
directions that our fluid can move in. And
dimensions that we're operating these equations
in. So in short, that entire left hand side,
the derivative of velocity is just acceleration.
And if we normalize mass, so it just equals 1.
It turns out that is mass time acceleration,
it is F= ma. The whole thing is F= ma. Yes,
it was just a more involved version of force
equals mass time acceleration this entire time.
Or the other way around. Guess technically it's
ma. MA equals F. There we are. Okay. So right,
the left is MA. On the right we got some force.
So uh first of all, this here is the viscosity.
new that little curvy V on the left. That's the
viscosity measure. And this is the leloian of the
velocity. That's just where you sum up all the
partial second derivatives. That just means the
fluid has some viscosity. And over here, this here
introduces P. That's the pressure. So, as well as
the force due to viscosity, we have the force due
to pressure. And finally, we had the force due to
a force. This is a smooth force that you can apply
to the fluid to move it around and that's going
to be super important in a moment. And now that we
understand all the terms involved, we can see what
it means to solve or I guess disprove the Navia
Stokes equation. And Clay gave four ways it can
be done. Um actually the first two are kind of the
same. It just depends what numbers you're using
um for the coordinates and the second two
are kind of the same. But if we zoom in on C,
which is what Open AI say they've done, we can uh
we can read it now. So on R3, so 3D coordinates,
that's new there. So that means it's got to
have nonzero viscosity. Fair enough. N= 3,
three dimensions. Good. So you got to show there
exists a smooth diversionfree vector field. Now
that's the um what I called u prime before. That's
just the starting conditions. a nice smooth moving
fluid at the beginning and then a smooth that's
important force that's the force we saw at the
very end the last term a moment ago which acts
on R3 and the conditions on statement C here is
you've got to show that the fluid ends up with
a singularity and that's got to happen in finite
time so that's why there's a curved bracket on
the end of our range here so time starts at zero
never quite reaches infinity so you can't just be
like Oh, asmtoically this will reach infinity. No,
it's got to happen in finite time. It's got to
use finite energy and it's got to be smooth,
a smooth force moving the fluid around. You can't
just like, you know, hit it with a hammer. So,
what does it mean that Open AI have found a
smooth force function that with finite energy
and finite time can produce a singularity?
And moreover, what on earth is this image
that everyone keeps memeing? We'll start with the
open AI page where they announced their solution.
In the beginning is just a very general, you
know, recap of the situation. The problem,
this is what we were saying before. Just going
through that, making sure everyone agrees on
what's happening there. And here's their result.
This is where it gets interesting. This first
sentence is the main bit. So they're establishing,
first of all, they've given an actual proof and a
lean formulization. So that's like basically
code that people can verify that their proof
is correct. Doesn't give you any insight, but
you can check it. And what they found is an
initially smooth fluid. So that was our starting
conditions. In fact, they've got it at rest.
And that could develop a singularity in finite
time. Now they say singularity that means that
it blows up in math's term. This is to say the
velocity is unbounded. it grows in a way where
it can become infinitely fast. You think, well,
hang on, that's not physically possible. Well,
it can be if the region in which it's happening
is getting smaller faster than the velocity
is getting bigger. And that's kind of the whole
point. That's how the energy remains finite. So,
it's physically plausible in in one sense, but
it still blows up, which means that the equations
don't work. And that's why this whole thing is
a counter example to Navia Stokes. And again,
the smooth force is the whole thing that makes
this so difficult. Now, you've already seen it
poking out the bottom here. Let's check out the
image. Here it is. Now, so OpenAI did produce
this themselves. People aren't just making it up.
However, it is a PR image. There's no code that
gives you this. It's not a 3D model. That was part
of the proof. It doesn't actually appear in the
proof at all. This is just an illustration for the
press release. So the teal bits are slow and then
the orange bits get faster and faster. But you can
see the orange bits along this axial stretching,
which we'll get to in a moment, is orange all
the way up and down. Now, if that was true,
this would be producing a singularity that runs
the entire kind of, you know, it' be a linear one
along the length of the axis. The singularity is
just a single region right in the middle at what
they describe as the origin. Now, that said, the
diagram is based on something. If we go back up
here and actually read the paper, which is always
important to do, and you scroll down a bit, you
can see there it is. This is the diagram that it
was based on. And even this isn't super accurate.
It's just a schematic to give you a rough sense of
what's happening. And it's also, as it says here,
it's exaggerated. So that meme image is a PR dress
up of an exaggerated schematic of the actual maths
OpenAI did. So let's talk about the maths. This is
showing three steps in the evolution of this fluid
as it approaches the singularity and everything's
been designed. So the singularity happens at time
t= 1 and then they define towa here as 1 minus t.
So this means toao is like the countdown until the
singularity happens. And the point is as you
get closer and closer to the singularity the
aspect ratio of this is changing. It's stretching
out. But oh my goodness, the reason they had to
exaggerate it here is h is your value for like
that's the exponent for the change in the aspect
ratio and that is always smaller than 100th. So
actually the aspect ratio changes so slowly as
tow approaches zero which is our big moment of
singularity. To help me get my head around it,
I made my own inaccurate diagram. Check it out.
So we are starting uh so toao is 0.3. So this is
closing in. We got less than a third of the time
left to singularity moment. And over here I've got
the max angular velocity which is a proxy of how
fast things are going in the middle. And you can
see now I've only got orange in the middle because
that's where the max speed is happening. It's not
happening all the way up and down this axis. So
let's set it going. Now on the left I've tried
to show that fluid is kind of spinning around
the axis and coming in near the middle let's
say and as it gets closer and closer it spins
faster classic and actually more is going out
the top than the bottom. Open AI are clear that
the asymmetry there is quite key however on the
left I'm keeping it fullsized on the right is
what's actually happening while it's spinning
and evolving. It's getting dramatically smaller
which I'm just showing by zooming out and you
can see tower is not going in a linear rate. All
the action happens right at the very end. That's
when the aspect ratio changes significantly and we
get exactly at tals 1 the singularity that breaks
the Navia Stokes equations. Please keep in mind
that this is just my ridiculous diagram and it's
super inaccurate as well. I just wanted to try
and give some kind of dynamic sense of the mass
situation that OpenAI were describing in their
paper. And if you want to go a tiny bit deeper,
what's interesting is OpenAI didn't find the
smooth force required to make this happen.
They found a setup like a velocity field. And so
that's what the diagrams trying to show you here.
And what they realized was if we come up to page
two, they point out for any incompressible flow uh
u that's our speed and pressure P, we can always
define the external force F to be the residue.
Which means you've got Navia Stokes explaining
all the standard fluid mechanics. So you take
the velocity field you need for the singularity.
You run it backwards through Navia Stokes and take
out all the fluid mechanics stuff and what is left
over has to be the additional force required to
get that velocity. But that force is so often not
smooth. And if you just set up this system here to
get the singularity, the force wouldn't be smooth.
What Open AI did, their real big breakthrough down
here on page six, they have a sequence of pulses
in the velocity and they had to tune a whole bunch
of these to make that spiral plausible, but in
such a way that the force comes out smooth. And
so this is what they actually designed was a
very clever way to pulse the velocity field to
get the singularity without making the force no
longer smooth. So have open AI actually solved a
millennium problem. The consensus seems to be yes.
They actually have. That said, their proof, their
result hasn't been verified independently yet and
they're a long way off actually getting the prize
awarded if indeed they even claim it. Wow. And
that brings us to the drama. The drama all kicked
off on Tuesday 8th of September. And the first
move was humans because OpenAI weren't the only
people working on this. Two human mathematicians,
Levvent Alpager, sorry I pronounced that wrong,
and Tristan Buckmaster were nearing a solution
themselves. Tristan actually put out a post on
Masttodon linking to three papers where they
had solved not the Navia Stokes but the very
similar Oiler equations which are the same thing
but with the viscosity removed so it's a little
bit easier and they had found a way to make the
Oiler equations break which means they would be
very close to doing the same thing for Navia
Stokes. The non-math drama then unfolded in a
statement that Tristan published at the same time
and it kind of falls into two different flavors.
One is that OpenAI heard the rumors and realized
some humans were close to claiming this Millennium
Prize and so they just pulled out all the stops
and powered up as they say 10,000 AI agents to
all work on it at the same time. Now this is
overkill. I mean it worked. They got there
first. But OpenAI do say that those agents sent
2.7 million messages and used about 130 billion
output tokens. A lot of people online have tried
to work out how much that would have costed if
you were actually paying for all those tokens.
And they figure that OpenAI spent between 10 to
40 million getting the Navia Stoke solution.
And that's discounting wasted tokens on other
Millennium prizes they may not have sold. But at
the end of the day, everyone used to be, "Wow,
Millennium prizes. They're like a million dollar
prize each." Now, someone has spent an order of
magnitude more money to win one. The second type
of drama is just messy drama. So, Tristan and
Levent did use Chat GPT's codeex to help write
some of their code, and they're like, well,
that end up in the training data that OpenAI used,
and OpenAI were like, well, we can't rule it out,
so that's a bit of a mess. And then there's all
these accusations that Open AI got in touch with
Tristan and said, "Oh, you can publish alongside
us, but you got to get rid of Elevant, who just
coincidentally happens to work at Anthropic,
a different AI company, even though they were
doing this work on their own time." And so there
was a lot of back and forth unpleasantness and
just just is not how academics ideally should be
behaving. Drama aside, mathematicians are also
pretty upset at how this one kind of oneshot
AI result was just dropped. And I've seen
that sold online as mathematicians just being
emotional because they're being replaced by AI,
which is a little bit true. But more importantly,
for the most part, mathematicians have been pro
good use of AI to help support mathematics
research. If you remember my previous video
where I mean which was like months ago now where
we looked at the oiler distance problem that was
discovered by AI thinking for like 80 minutes and
then just dumping a result but it had techniques
and methods within that and they've already been
repurposed by humans to solve other things. And
so mathematicians are not just like blanket AI is
bad. They're like the way we're using AI now is
bad. Specifically in this case, mathematicians are
really annoyed because it was a counter example
dropped in a way that's not human understandable.
There's no insight we can get from this other than
we know there's a counter example. And moreover,
that means it's less likely mathematicians will
work on this problem because we kind of already
know the answer, which means we're going to
skip everything in between from wondering about
the problem to eventually solving it. And sure,
we could just say, look, reverse engineer the
oneshot counter example and see what you learn.
But humans are humans. We're not going to have the
same motivation if we already know the ending. And
the journey is the whole point. Much like a roller
coaster at a theme park, see tied it in. Also,
yes, it is the next day, right? The journey is
the experience. And we're going to miss out a
lot of maths if we don't do that journey. I mean,
in the past, if an AI had one shot and said, you
can't square the circle, would we have bothered
inventing transcendental numbers? If AI had said,
there are no solutions to the quintic, do we still
get galwis theory? that we have to still be doing
the journey. And actually my uh close personal
friend Grant Sanderson of three blue one brown
fame is doing a blog post on Terry Tal's blog and
their own video which we're coming out about now
due to the nature of breaking news. I don't know
if this video will be first or theirs. You should
absolutely check that out. It's got a really good
insight into why we do the journey of mathematics.
All of that said, for the longest time,
mathematicians have been saying, "Keep funding
us because the maths we're doing might one day be
useful. Just trust us, bro." And mathematicians,
we may have applied maths ourselves into the
corner. And now society is saying, "Yeah,
if mathematics is as useful as you say, and
maybe it's more like a monorail ride where the
destination is the point, then surely we should
just fire up the AI mass machine and spit out as
many results as we can to see if they're useful."
And uh I kind of got a point there. In one sense,
Navia Stokes was the worst millennium problem to
be a first because it sounds so applied. We care
about fluids. We want to know how they move.
But in reality, for the longest time, anyone
doing actual fluid mechanics already knew the
limitations of Navia Stokes and how to calculate
the movement of fluid in any practical situation.
The Millennium Prize version was very much pure
math dressed up in fluid mechanics. And I quite
enjoyed on the fluid mechanics subreddit. Uh
someone actually ran the numbers for a real fluid
to see what would happen and it would vaporize
long before that singularity. So for all practical
purposes, this discovery is actually not helping
humans at all. And look, if OpenAI had found
a new way to I don't know, multiply matrices,
everyone would be very excited. No one would
be complaining, "Ooh, you didn't show us you're
working out." We'd be like, "Great, new way to
multiply matrices." which is what happened back in
2025 when I did the video about Deep Mind coming
up with a better 4x4 complex number matrix form of
multiplication. There are definitely new applied
bits of mathematics techniques and algorithms that
AI can help us find and implement and we should
all celebrate that. But just picking off pure
bits of mathematics with no immediate application
is just going to undermine both the education and
the motivation to discover and learn more pure
mathematics. And that is a very different subject.
That's the one where the journey is the point
because what we learn along the way and little
detours we notice and we hadn't previously
considered taking. So what happens now? Well,
I think in some regard a lot of people thought
something like this was inevitable. I would have
guessed some kind of neural network LLM linked up
to some kind of proofbearing firing lean system
but it would have been like a niche thing that
mathematicians had. I did not see it becoming this
kind of, you know, Silicon Valley startup culture,
move fast, break things situation where now maths
specifically has become this tech [music] bro
appendage measuring competition to just dump
big answers out there. Although that said, given
the response to Navia Stokes, I I I believe the AI
companies are sitting on a war chest of big mass
results and they're going to try and work out how
to release them. And I say, please just just do
it [music] do it nicely. But all of that aside,
one day this will all settle down. We'll have a
magical math box over here finding better ways
to multiply matrices. And over here we'll have
AI helping mathematicians better understand and
discover new bits of mathematics. I just hope
we get there get there quickly. Uh [music] but
it's unavoidable. The the AI tide is coming
in. I think it's important we have a kind of
societywide nuance conversation about this. Surely
that's that's what's going to happen. Anyway,
that's it. This time I won't do another one one of
these for a while unless there's some ridiculous
breaking mass news. We'll see what happens. Uh,
one day I'll just have a regular vacation. Oh, now
that said, I have actually been here doing some
work. The video will be out probably in November.
Subscribe if you want to see it. But this this
actual video, this is nothing to do with Disney
or anyone else. This was literally me on vacation
and thought this would be fun to put together. In
fact, I've accidentally brought two overqualified
filmmakers to help me uh put this video together.
So now, much like the poor crying children at
the end of a day out at Epcot, we're going to
wrap this up. Uh, you should say thanks to my poor
friends who just want to go back to their holiday.